Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组 Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
What did those vile lackeys say?
A full confession was obtained.
Besides plotting to murder Noble Consort Lumière,
much more was choked out of them.
Even more?
The other matters are trifling,
except for one that I dare not hold back from Your Majesty.
What is it?
Your Majesty,
the death of Empress Première...
was... was connected to the Empress.
How dare you!
I dare not lie to Your Majesty.
Speak. Don't spare a single detail!
Yes.
Your Majesty, two foods were added to Empress Premier's meals.
According to the Imperial doctors,
hardy banana is harmless to eat in small amounts;
however, pregnant women must not touch it due to its cold nature.
Hardy banana has a downward draining effect,
similar to peach kernel and safflower seed.
Its medicinal efficacy is not as strong as safflower,
but when the fruit is cooked, the effect does seep into the food.
Over time it will harm the body.
Additionally, the almonds in her almond tea
were replaced by peach kernels, which could harm the pregnancy.
Mixed in the tea, the taste is indistinguishable.
These two substances were added
to Empress Première's food all along.
Did this come from the mouths of those servants?
Autumn was subjected to every cruel torture,
but didn't reveal anything.
But Jiang Fuhai
confessed everything.
Besides that, the black and blue bruises on the body
of Empress Première's stillborn child provide ironclad proof.
Wasn't the stillbirth because the other Lord Consort
caused the Empress Première anxiety and fear?
The imperial doctor said that explanation
easily concealed the real plot.
So it was really her.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Besides this plot against Empress Première,
there are many others.
I always thought
Première was her dear sister.
She attended Première
with humility and deference.
Bring her here.
We have been husband and wife for many years.
I believe she plotted
to influence the selection of Crown Prince.
I can also believe
she harmed the concubines and the imperial heirs.
But this matter of Première -
I need to hear from her own lips.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Now that it's come to this,
will you admit your crimes?
Your Majesty already believes it.
Why do you need to ask me?
If not to hear you confess to your crimes,
do you think I could tolerate seeing your face?
I've grown old and my beauty has faded.
Of course Your Majesty is averse to seeing me.
It makes me wonder:
if my sister were still alive,
would Your Majesty still wholeheartedly love her aging face ?
Now I am filled with regret.
I should have let Your Majesty watch
her beauty decay,
like mine.
Maybe Your Majesty wouldn't hate me so much then.
Beauty comes from a kind heart.
Even if Première had grown old,
she would be worth ten thousand of you.
Your Majesty put this pair of bracelets on my wrists
when we were first married.
"I hope we see each other day and night like these bracelets."
Now Your Majesty believes that I've done wrong,
and perhaps doesn't wish to see me anymore.
At that time,
with these bracelets in hand, Your Majesty told me
that if I gave birth to a son,
you would make me your primary wife.
But when my son was born,
you had already married my sister as your primary wife.
My child would only be the son of a secondary wife,
just like I am,
and could never be rid of this mark.
You know I never cared about the primacy status.
Neither did Imperial Mother care.
Imperial Mother was born of a secondary wife.
Even I was born of a secondary wife.
Your Majesty, how could you ever know
how painful life is for the daughter of a secondary wife?
Our mother's standing dictates our lifelong status.
My mother and I were never highly regarded.
Did you ever understand?
I did understand.
That was exactly why
I treated you generously after you entered my estate.
Even though I made Première my primary wife,
you were second only to her.
But you were never content!
The title of primary wife should have been mine;
it was handed to her!
My son's prospects to become Crown Prince
were ground underfoot!
All the love from my husband was given to her.
I wanted to be content,
but I couldn't make myself!
Première was your sister!
It was my mistake to have married you.
Your Majesty's mistake wasn't marrying me into the estate,
but marrying Première
and favoring her exclusively.
"Since Yu was already born, why was Liang ever born?"
Your Majesty is wise,
why couldn't you understand the pertinence of this saying.
I overestimated the sisterhood between you.
Don't you fear Heaven's retribution?
When you dream at night,
aren't you afraid that Première and her son
will come to you, demanding your life?
If she wants my life, let her come!
Better than me dreaming of my own child
crying to me every long, endless night.
When my son died,
she became pregnant.
Your Majesty was so engrossed in the joy of her pregnancy.
Did you even remember the child I had with you?
He was only three years old,
burning up from high fever
and no treatment could help him!
I carried his dead body in my arms
and walked in the rain all night.
I wanted to walk to the judge of the underworld
and beg all the Buddhas and gods:
if they had to take one life,
take mine instead of my son's!
Première became pregnant at that very moment!
Wasn't it her son who took my son's life?!
How could I bear to see her son
become the heir to the throne?
You've lost your mind!
It was I who insisted on marrying Première.
It was I who demanded to make her my primary wife.
It was I who had a child with her.
Why didn't you hate me instead?
Your Majesty thinks I didn't want to?
How much I wished to hate you...
but I couldn't make myself!
I couldn't make myself!
Your Majesty had only Première in your eyes.
But has Your Majesty ever known that
my love for you
is no less than yours for her?
Your Majesty,
do you think Première loved you so much?
Do you think Noble Consort Lumière really loves you?
How can any woman who truly loves her husband
willingly allow herself to see her husband
loving other women and having children with them?
I couldn't make myself!
Your Majesty thinks I'm crazed with jealousy,
but it's because I am truly and deeply in love with you!
The words of a Buddha and the heart of a snake.
You disgust me.
Your Majesty,
if I were not defending myself as the Empress,
I would also wish that
Your Majesty remember the goodness about me,
no matter how little.
How I wish I never had to conceal anything from Your Majesty.
Practicing virtue so reluctantly
became the greatest sorrow of my life.
"The Empress from the Ula-Nara family
is not blessed by Heaven due to her deceitful nature.
She harmed imperial heirs and incited factions in court,
and thus is unworthy to be the Mother of the Nation
and entering the imperial shrine.
She is to be demoted to commoner and relocated to
the Cold Palace."
Bring my red seal.
Yes.
I have come here this late night to seek an audience with Your Majesty.
What brings you here, Madam Bamboo?
Your Majesty, I know an important change
is happening in the palace tonight.
To assist Your Majesty's judgement,
I've brought the Empress Dowager's edict.
Imperial Mother left a decree?
I dare not deceive Your Majesty.
When I finish reading Her Majesty's decree,
Your Majesty may have a look for yourself.
It is in Her Majesty's own handwriting.
Wait one moment while I depose this malicious woman.
The edict relates to today's crisis.
Please kneel and receive Her Majesty's decree.
The posthumous edict of the Empress Dowager:
"After my passing, even in the case of a major offence,
the Emperor must take heed:
The Empress from the Ula-Nara clan shall not be deposed."
It is indeed Imperial Mother's handwriting.
"As you, Lady Ula-Nara, from a prestigious lineage
blessed with bell chimes of auspice and raiments of glory,
are gentle and kind in heart
and manifest them in your manner；
you fulfill the Six Conducts and emanate graceful virtues.
You will exalt the Four Teachings of Confucius in the palace
and enlighten all under Heaven as Mother of the Nation.
At the Empress Dowager's benevolent behest,
you are conferred the Golden Book and the title of Empress.
Reverently."
That was the edict by which Your Majesty
made me your Empress.
Does Your Majesty still remember?
Your Majesty rules with benevolence and filial piety,
and must not disregard the will of the Empress Dowager.
This edict was also the reason
that I didn't join Her Majesty under the Nine Springs.
Nonetheless, Ula-Nara's crime cannot be pardoned.
I have no choice but to depose her -
to appease Première's spirit under the Nine Springs.
I hope Imperial Mother may calm her anger.
Before the Empress Dowager passed away,
she enjoined me to ask Your Majesty one question
if Your Majesty proceeded with deposing the Empress:
Does Your Majesty recall
when Empress Première lay dying in your arms,
what were her last words?
Première was breathing so feebly...
She rested her head on my knees
and said to me:
"My life is not blessed -
too short to grow gray and old with Si Lang.
I couldn't even save our child.
I only have one younger sister, Yixiu.
From now on, I hope Si Lang can treat her well come what may,
and never desert her."
Your Majesty gave Empress Première your word
that you would never desert her sister.
Your Majesty's forgiveness of the Empress today
is to bring peace to Empress Première's spirit.
Your Majesty despises the Empress
so much so that you don't address her by name
and keep calling her Ula-Nara.
But wasn't Empress Première an Ula-Nara as well?
Wasn't the Empress Dowager a member of the Ula-Nara clan?
Even Your Majesty is part Ula-Nara by blood.
The Empress Dowager's edict says:
"The Empress from the Ula-Nara clan shall not be deposed."
To honor my feelings for those departed,
Ula-Nara shall dwell in the Palace of Great Benevolence
and never leave until her death.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Go to the Palace of Great Benevolence
and retrieve the Empress's enthronement edict,
the Golden Book and Golden Seal.
Announce my decree to the palace:
She and I
shall never meet again in life or death.
I obey Your Majesty's decree.
You dolt.
The hellish noise of the cicadas -
Can't you hear it?
Find someone to remove them with a sticky pole.
You'll lose your heads if the dragon is bothered!
Your Majesty, the Dzungar Khagan Galdan is boldly ambitious.
He is leading four hundred thousand cavalry
towards the Yanming Pass.
If they break through the Yanming Pass,
the capital city will be in danger.
I've been aware of Khagan Galdan's ambition.
These years I have been busy with land regulation,
and strife in the capital.
I had no hand to deal with him.
Dzungar is merely a grassland tribe.
Now they have set their minds on challenging me.
Your Majesty has just quelled the northwest.
And the tribal leaders in the southwest
are still rebelling one after another.
The budgets of the Treasury and Ministry of War
grow tighter year by year.
If Galdan sends in troops now,
we will indeed be unprepared.
I sent Generals Yue Zhongqi and Fuerdan,
but they cannot endure the hot weather.
Many soldiers are overcome by heat stroke and cannot fight.
At the moment, it will be difficult
to deploy another good general.
"Easier to gather thousands of soldiers
than to find one good general."
May Your Majesty forgive my major offense by asking.
If we could send Lord XIV...
Not appropriate.
"Easier to set the tiger free than to catch him again."
If my fourteenth brother isn't rid of his rebellious bones,
he will be a major threat if he is freed.
What happened to His Majesty?
We are so quick to offend him.
How should I serve him now?
Haven't you seen those piles of memoranda?
His Majesty is almost buried in them.
How can you serve?
Pretend it is your head on the serving platter.
Shifu, good thing you're directly serving His Majesty.
By the way, the Palace of Eternal Longevity sent people here twice
to invite His Majesty for dinner.
His Majesty only had a few bites at breakfast,
and scarcely touched lunch.
His energy is hanging on the ginseng soup.
His eyes are red and tired.
What actually happened to His Majesty?
What's happened? Ask Heaven.
What is Your Majesty's opinion?
A state prince is the best choice to represent me on the battlefield.
After thinking it through,
Noble Prince Guo is the top choice.
His mother's humble background constrains
any inappropriate ambitions.
Besides, he respects boundaries.
Your Majesty is meticulous in your deliberation.
I revere Your Majesty's order.
He is into books and poetry.
I will confer a title on him in name only.
As for the generals, you must deploy wisely.
I understand.
Make sure it's done quietly.
Allocate State Prince Guo two thousand men
from the Valiant Cavalry.
Once the front line is more stable,
send him to guard the Yanming Pass.
Yes.
Close the windows. I don't want to hear the wind.
At Yanming Pass "the frightful wind resembles
as the roars of the enemy,"
yet Your Majesty's divine wisdom can command the wind and rain.
Have a look at this.
Dzungar asks the Great Qing
to award them three million taels a year.
This Galdan is the new Khagan of Dzungar.
He is young, and his appetite is too great.
He asks this
to test the real strength of the Great Qing
and to drum up grounds for starting a war.
Galdan aims to shake the Great Qing at its roots.
Your Majesty must not approve.
Of course I won't.
He dares to be so reckless
because he is confident in his troops and provisions.
I should not underestimate him.
Your Majesty, Mr. Zhang Tingyu requests an audience.
Yes.
Your Majesty, I will take my leave.
Peace to Your Majesty.
You may rise.
Your Majesty,
General Yue Zhongqi sent messengers dashing overnight
to report that a plague has been spreading
among the Dzungar troops.
Heaven blesses our Great Qing.
Today, Dzungar sent an envoy
requesting an audience for Khagan Galdan with Your Majesty.
What could be his intention in coming to Beijing now?
Galdan has long coveted the Great Qing.
Although they are stricken by the plague,
they still have a few hundred thousand soldiers
and plentiful supplies.
Your Majesty, we must remain wary.
Send someone there to find out
the cause of the plague.
I remember I ordered Dr. Wen
to keep the prescriptions for the plague.
It may be useful in the future.
Yes.
Elder sister, we cannot let His Lordship go to the front.
Setting aside the danger of blades and spears,
His Majesty is wary due to His Lordship's great talent.
Regarding military prowess,
the fate of State Prince Dun is the example we see.
We both know of His Majesty's temperament.
His Lordship cannot swim against the tide.
If His Lordship insists on declining,
the only reason he can give is this:
to call himself incompetent.
Only this will ease His Majesty's mind,
and keep His Lordship from suspicion.
Does His Lordship have to go?
The court is in need of assistance.
There are not many State Princes that His Majesty can send.
No wonder Yunxi is madly restless at home.
In this crisis, of course he wants to serve at the battlefield.
But none of his memorandums
received a response from His Majesty.
Venerable Prince Shen is still young.
There are plenty of opportunities ahead of him.
He is just upset to see his seventeenth brother given duties
while he himself receives stipends for doing nothing.
I give up.
His Lordship's wish has finally been granted.
But I cannot be more worried.
The battlefield yields no mercy.
Who knows what dangers await?
I've heard that Galdan is already at the relay station.
But Your Majesty is in no hurry to summon him.
I am correcting his hostile temperament.
Galdan has come far in the summer heat.
Your Majesty's method
will also cool his internal Heat.
In two days, it will be the seventh of the seventh month.
I will move to the Summer Palace and meet him there.
Zhang Tingyu has been arranging it.
Your Majesty,
Galdan is outside waiting for an audience.
Summon him in.
Yes.
Khagan Galdan is summoned by His Majesty.
We Dzungars are not shy about what we like.
We do everything we can to acquire it.
Our Khagan is here to pay his respects
to the Emperor of the Great Qing.
Dzungar comes to pay respect,
so why don't you follow the protocol of the Great Qing
when greeting His Majesty?
"Isn't it a pleasure to have friends visit from afar?"
[from The Analects, in Dzungar language]
Today is the seventh of the seventh month.
His Majesty is treating family and friends with a family banquet.
Khagan, you said in your own language
"It's a pleasure to have friends visit from afar."
you should also know:
"The Noble Man is reverential and orderly in his own conduct,
and respectful to others and observant of the proprieties.
Then all within the four seas will be his brothers."
[quoted from The Analects]
My old friend, I haven't seen you for so long.
Khagan is still as spirited as ever.
It seems Khagan is very fond of The Analects of Confucius.
My seventeenth brother, State Prince Guo
is well-versed in prose and poetry.
You can speak further with him when you have time.
Han people pour wine onto the ground to honor the dead.
You are cursing me!
Khagan misunderstands. I am not cursing you.
I am greeting Khagan with the etiquette for noble guests.
Khagan is a noble guest to the Nation of Heaven,
so the first cup of wine
thanks "Imperial Heaven and Earth" for leading our delightful guest here.
Your explanation is far-fetched.
There is no need to see fault.
The relationship between the Great Qing and Dzungar
has been the trade of goods.
But recently we have been greeted with armaments.
Dzungar has already been subject to the Great Qing,
but now is warring on a battlefield.
This inevitably drives us apart.
If your visit today, Khagan
can bring peaceful coexistence between the Great Qing and Dzungar,
we will have more familiarity and fewer misunderstandings.
It will be fortunate for the common people.
Your Noble Highness is clever with words.
You don't sound like a woman
who has never stepped out of the harem.
Khagan, I hope I did not incur ridicule from you.
I am lacking in talent and knowledge.
What little I know is owed to occasions when I received
His Majesty's enlightenment.
I do not merit Khagan's generous compliment.
Noble Consort Lumière's words are agreeable to my heart.
Khagan, please drink this cup
to celebrate the joy of us meeting.
Very well. I wish the Emperor of the Great Qing
undisturbed blessings and unending longevity.
Sit.
My attendant.
Yes.
Today is the seventh of the seventh month,
the day of "begging for craftiness".
I have an ingenious item to share with everyone.
Many years ago, I obtained these Nine-Linked Jade Rings.
I heard that an artisan of the Western Regions risked his life
to find this beautiful jade,
and exerted his mind to carve it into the nine rings.
I have heard there are many wise men in the Central Plains.
May I ask the Emperor of Great Qing
to solve this puzzle for me?
Display it for all the officials to see.
The one who solves it will be greatly rewarded.
Aye.
Let the song and dance begin.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Minister, His Majesty has decreed
whoever can untie this nine-ring puzzle will be rewarded.
Minister, please take a look.
Show them to this minister.
Sir, please take a look.
Minister.
Please take a look.
No, I cannot.
Minister, please.
What do you think?
These rings may as well have been carved by Heaven.
There is no way to disconnect them.
Please take a closer look. Look carefully.
Your Majesty,
no one could unlink the rings.
Show them to the princes.
Aye.
Go away!
They make my eyes dizzy.
I don't know either, Your Majesty.
Yunxi.
I have never been fond of gold and gems.
I don't know much about them.
Noble Consort Lumière.
Your Majesty, I'm incompetent.
So saying: "The Great Qing has many wise men"
is simply incorrect.
Longyue.
Then, you will first...
Father, I have a way that may unlink the rings.
Even the government officials could not find a solution.
What can a little girl like you do?
I am young and unskilled.
Even if my way is wrong, no one will laugh at me.
Imperial Father, why not let me have a try?
Might as well.
Imperial Father, I unlinked them.
Longyue is favorite in my heart!
No need to praise me for my intelligence.
The people of the Great Qing all know this method.
They just didn't bother to show you.
You! The Nine-Linked Jade Rings are priceless.
The "priceless" treasure to you
is only a common item to me.
If Dzungar's emissary loses his manners over a jade ring,
it will make the Dzungars look cheap.
Even if you regard the rings as ordinary,
they are still a treasure of the Dzungars.
You destroyed our treasure.
How will you resolve that?
Longyue.
The princess is young.
Khagan, please calm your anger.
Congratulations, Khagan!
The princess has brought a sign
of peace and harmony to the Dzungars.
Jade has a yin nature.
Excess yin gravely damages one's merit.
It is very ill-omened.
By breaking the jade rings the princess
has indeed dispelled such ominous energy
and brought auspiciousness to the Dzungars.
Indeed. It's natural that Khagan is disgruntled by the broken jade.
Why not ask skilled jewelers in the palace
to make it into gold-inlaid jade rings?
The yang energy of gold
will balance the yin energy of jade,
becoming an omen of good fortune and peace.
Noble Consort Estime's thoughts are excellent.
The broken jade can be repaired.
But if two countries break their relations, war is inevitable.
Just as we reform jade with gold,
why don't we transform our spears into jade-inlaid gifts?
Khagan, are you willing to do so?
A mere ant tries to stop a mighty beast.
What do you think will happen, Emperor?
Your Majesty,
this orange wine is freshly made.
Please have a taste.
Mr. Zhang Tingyu asked me to report to Your Majesty
that General Yue Zhongqi has succeeded.
Beasts have their strength,
yet ants have their own type of wisdom.
Khagan, do you really think success is guaranteed?
It seems the ants are retreating step by step.
"Retreating, in order to advance."
I believe Khagan is familiar with military books.
I certainly would like to believe so.
I hope it's not just "empty words from smacking lips."
Khagan teases me.
As the Son of Heaven, my words carry weight.
I heard that the Dragon has nine sons.
There could be more than one "Son of Heaven".
"Born of the same root, why be hasty to fight each other?"
Dzungar has been a part of the Great Qing,
so naturally I take an interest.
I heard the Dzungar army has been afflicted
with an illness at the Yanming Pass.
The army is away from home,
and medical supplies may be limited.
A few years ago, the Great Qing also experienced a plague.
I know of effective remedies.
If you need them, Khagan,
I can send someone to look for them.
Thank you, Emperor, for your kind offer.
I will send my own men to search for them.
All right then.
But these doctors travel all over the country
and carry the formulas with them.
Even if I send someone to find them now,
it may still take two to three months.
I hope everything goes smoothly for you, Khagan.
Your Majesty, please allow me to go get changed.
-Your Highness.
-Mr. Su.
Good news!
General Yue Zhongqi pretended to confront the Dzungar army,
but secretly sent elite cavalry to raid their supply lines.
Without food and supplies,
and with the Dzungar soldiers afflicted by the plague,
I would like to see how this Galdan can still act so arrogantly!
-This is excellent news.
-Indeed.
His Majesty will surely be pleased to hear about this.
I'll be there right away.
Yes, Your Highness.
A moment of your time, Your Highness!
Grace to Khagan.
It's been a long time, is Your Noble Highness well?
Your words confuse me, Khagan.
I never met Khagan before.
Why did you say "a long time"?
I have the eyes of an eagle,
and can remember any face at a glance.
Noble Consort Lumière,
you are so very daring
to have committed adultery with the Emperor's brother!
I have never offended Khagan.
Why would you accuse me of a crime
that could cost my family their lives?
Are you afraid I'll tell your Emperor the story of the past?
What "story of the past"?
My sister is Noble Prince Guo's Lord Consort.
We look quite alike.
I heard years ago she was traveling with His Lordship
and happened to find Khagan injured by a snake.
Today old friends meet again.
They have said they hope to "clink goblets" with the Khagan.
Noble Consort Lumière,
you surely have a way with words.
A woman as intelligent and beautiful as you
is not only adored by your Emperor
but by me as well.
Khagan must be drunk.
I'll go inform His Majesty, and order Khagan a tonic to sober up.
No need for that.
Do you really think I'm afraid of your Emperor?
He sneakily burned our food and supplies,
and used the plague to threaten me.
What despicable tricks!
Khagan must know "Deception is a strategy in warfare."
"Misery - happiness is to be found by its side!
Happiness - misery lurks beneath it! "
Noble Consort Lumière,
don't you think I will find a way to gain from this loss?
So long as this war ends,
it will be a gain and blessing for both the Great Qing and the Dzungars.
I can only hope your Emperor is willing to give me what I want.
Your Majesty,
By Your Majesty's order, I've investigated it.
It was true.
Have your department make a thorough investigation,
and you must find evidence.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Khagan Galdan requests an audience
regarding an important matter.
What important matter?
Khagan said there's something he greatly desires
and asks Your Majesty to grant it to him.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.